The music and the magic come together...
'Round Midnight is a drama, music film directed by Bertrand Tavernier.
Inside the Blue Note nightclub one night in 1959 Paris, an aged,
ailing jazzman coaxes an eloquent wail from his tenor sax.
Outside, a young Parisian too broke to buy a glass
of wine strains to hear those notes.
Soon they will form a friendship that sparks a final burst of genius.
Dale Turner, played by Dexter Gordon.
Francis Borler, played by François Cluzet.
Bérangère, played by Gabrielle Haker.
Sylvie, played by Christine Pascal.
le père de Francis, played by Pierre Trabaud.
la mère de Francis, played by Frédérique Meininger.
Round Midnight is a 1986 American musical drama film directed by
Bertrand Tavernier and written by Tavernier and David Rayfiel.
It stars Dexter Gordon, with a soundtrack by Herbie Hancock.
The title comes from Thelonious Monk's 1943 composition "'Round Midnight",
which is featured in this film in a Hancock arrangement.
The protagonist jazzman, Dale Turner, is based on a composite of real-life
jazz legends Lester Young (tenor sax) and Bud Powell (piano).
While the film is fictionalized, it is drawn directly from the memoir/biography Dance of the Infidels written by French author
Francis Paudras, who had befriended Powell during his Paris expatriate days and on whom the character Francis was based.
Gordon was nominated for the Academy Award for Best Actor and won a Grammy for the film's soundtrack entitled
The Other Side of Round Midnight in the category for Best Instrumental Jazz Performance, Soloist.
Hancock won the Academy Award for Best Original Score.
The soundtrack was released in two parts: Round Midnight
and The Other Side of Round Midnight.
The film explores themes of jazz, musician, jazz singer
or musician, saxophonist, saxophone.
The tone is emotional.